
<!--********************************************************************-->

<section xml:id="sec-Matlab_InputOutput_HW" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Input/Output Homework Problems</title>

	<p>
		When you submit this assignment, there should be three separate files.  Problems 1 and 2 should be in their own function m-files (properly commented of course).  Problems 3-6 should be a separate script m-file that uses the code from the first 2 problems and Excel spreadsheets on Angel.  
		<ol>
			<li>
				<p>
					For this problem, you will modify your projectile motion function from the homework in section <xref ref="sec-Matlab_userdefined_functions"/>.  Now, as part of your new function, <c>ProjMotion2</c>, plot the <c>height</c> versus <c>time</c>, use <c>ginput</c> for the user to identify the maximum height, and use <c>fprintf</c> to display a sentence describing the maximum height and corresponding time.    
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					For this problem, modify your conversion function from the previous homeworhomework in section <xref ref="sec-Matlab_userdefined_functions"/> and rename it <c>Conversion2</c>.  Now, use <c>fprintf</c> in order to create a nice-looking table showing conversions between Dollar, Euro, Yen, and British Pounds.  Include a header for each column.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Run your ProjMotion2 function for <c>time</c> 0 to 30 seconds (in increments of 0.5 seconds) and your function <c>Conversion2</c> for <c>dollars</c> from 0 to 100 in increments of 5.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Data on the Federal GDP and Deficit (as a percentage of GDP) is in a file called GDPAndDeficitByYear.xlsx (in the Appendix in Table <xref ref="table-GDPDeficit_a"/>).  First save this file to a directory on your computer and then use the command <c>xlsread</c> to load this file.  Assign the data in the file to a variable of your choice and create a plot of year (1st column) versus GDP (2nd column, in billions of dollars) including appropriate titles and labels on the axes.  Use <c>ginput</c> for the user to click on the first time the GDP exceeds \$10 trillion.  Use <c>fprintf</c> to display the information in a useful way.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Consider the data from the previous problem (loaded with <c>xlsread</c> from the file called <c>GDPAndDeficitByYear.xlsx</c>).  Now create a plot of year versus Deficit (3rd column), which is listed as a percentage of the GDP for the corresponding year.  Including appropriate titles and labels on the axes.  Use <c>ginput</c> for the user to click on {\bf all} of the times the Deficit percentage has hit 10 percent and then use <c>fprintf</c> to display the information in a useful way.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Data on unemployment percentages (per month) during 2000-2010 is in a file called <c>UnemploymentByYear.xlsx</c> (in the Appendix in Table <xref ref="table-Unemployment"/>).  First save this file to a directory on your computer and then use the command <c>xlsread</c> to load this file.  Note that the first row of the file is text so you will only want to load the information on rows 2 through 12.  Assign the data in the file to a variable of your choice.  Since the data for December 2010 has not been entered, correct it (in Matlab) with the correct value (look it up online).  Next, create a plot of month versus unemployment (including appropriate titles and labels on the axes).  Your plot should have 11 curves, one for each year and in different colors.  Include a legend in your plot for reference (labelled correctly).
				</p>
			</li>
		</ol>

		<!-- EXERCISES: -->
		<!-- 1)For this problem, you will modify your projectile motion function, <m>&lt;</m>vmiid<m>&gt;</m>ProjMotion, from the last homework.  Now, as part of your function, plot the height from 0 to 30 seconds, use ginput to get maximum height and use fprintf to display a sentence describing the maximum height and corresponding time. -->
		<!-- \vspace{1in} -->
		<!-- 2) For this problem, modify your conversion function from the previous homework and include fprintf in order to create a nice-looking table showing conversions between Dollar, Euro, Yen, and British Pounds.   -->
		<!-- Include a header for each column and use 0 to 100 dollars in increments of 5. -->
	</p>

</section>


