
<!--********************************************************************-->
 
<section xml:id="sec-Matlab_MonteCarlo_HW" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>Monte Carlo Exercises</title>
 
	<p>
		For each HW problem, include a well-labelled plot that shows the shapes and the points selected through the Monte Carlo process.
	</p>

	<ol>
		<li>
			<p>
				Area of a circle

				Find the area of the unit circle by putting it in a larger square with corners at <m>(\pm 2, \pm 2)</m> and using the fact that the bigger square has area 16.  Compare with the correct answer, found using a geometrical argument.
			</p>
		</li>
		<li>
			<p>
				Area of a hexagon

						Find the area of the regular hexagon inscribed in the unit circle by putting it in a larger square with corners at <m>(\pm 2, \pm 2)</m> and using the fact that the bigger square has area 16. Compare with the correct answer, found using a geometrical argument.

			</p>
		</li>
		<li>
			<p>
				Areas of sections of overlapping figures

				Find the areas of the three regions that are created by the unit circle and the square with corners at <m>(-0.5,-0.5),</m>
				<m>(1.5,-0.5),</m>
				<m>(1.5,1.5),</m>
				<m>(-0.5,1.5)</m>.  Put both figures in a larger square with corners at <m>(\pm 2, \pm 2)</m> and use the fact that the bigger square has area 16.  Compare with the correct answers, found using geometrical arguments or calculus.
			</p>
		</li>
		<li>
			<p>
				Area under a simple curve

				Find the area under the curve <m>y = x^2+2</m> from <m>x = 0</m> to <m>x = B</m>, where <m>B</m> is input by the user.  The larger square (or perhaps rectangle) will now have to be found in terms of <m>B</m>.   For a few values of <m>B</m> of your choice, compare the area with the correct answer, found using calculus.

			</p>
		</li>
		<li>
			<p>
				Area under the normal curve

				Find the area under the normal curve of mean 0 and standard deviation 1 from <m>x = A</m> to <m>x = B</m> where <m>A</m> and <m>B</m> are input by the user.  The larger square (or perhaps rectangle) will now have to be found in terms of <m>A</m> and <m>B</m>.   You may assume that <m>A&lt;B</m> and both are between -4 and 4.  Compare your answer in the case <m>A = –1, B = 2</m> the area with the correct answer, found using calculus techniques.
			</p>
		</li>
		<li>
			<p>
				Conclusions

				What can you say about the Monte Carlo method in its use for finding areas?
			</p>
		</li>
	</ol>

</section>


